A Guide to the Hedrick Family Collection, 1856-1959: SC 0171
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Hedrick Family Papers
1856-1959
Special Collections, James Madison University
Hedrick Family
SC 0171
.17 cubic feet; 1 box
The Hedrick Family Collection, 1856-1959, consists financial documents, correspondence and digitized account books, and miscellaneous documents belonging to the Hedrick family of the Elkton and McGaheysville Virginia area.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Gift of James C. Hedrick III, April 29, 2008.
Biographical Information
The Hedrick family has been a part of the Elkton community for many generations. During the French and Indian War, a George Hedrick was listed as an Augusta County soldier [later Rockingham County]. During the Civil War, a George W. Hedrick and C.L Hedrick served in the River Rangers, a Confederate cavalry from East Rockingham County, while an H.C. Hedrick served under Company A, 3rd Battalion, Virginia Reserves.
Scope and Content
The Hedrick Family Collection, 1870-1959, is comprised of legal documents, financial documents, correspondence, ephemera and digitized account books.
Legal documents include a large number of summonses addressed to George W. Hedrick to appear before Rockingham County Court. The second folder includes documents pertaining to tax and tax collection. Some examples include receipts for paid taxes from both Rockingham County and the Commonwealth of Virginia. Of particular interest is a signed letter from former governor Harry Flood Byrd to Mr. Hedrick discussing new tax policy in 1927. Personal financial documents include bank notes from Rockingham Bank and the First National Bank of Harrisonburg, promissory notes involving the harvesting of wheat crops, and a document regarding the Stonewall Road Board in 1900 that itemizes equipment and labor costs to be reimbursed to James C. Hedrick. Receipts from locations such as the Wetzel Seed Company, the United Wool Grower's Association, Shenandoah Valley Livestock Sales, and the Rockingham Petroleum Cooperative are also represented. Correspondence consists of letters and envelopes, several of which contain unique stamps and cancellations. Most of the correspondence in this series is personal and usually between cousins, brothers, sisters, and friends. Miscellaneous, 1892-1922, consists of three publications and handwritten documents describing the establishment of a Reform Church of McGaheysville, campaign business cards for the office of Commissioner of the Revenue for Plains District, and a certificate of promotion for James Hedrick from "B" class to "A" class of second grade from 1905. One of the church publications is an abstract of acts and proceedings of the Reformed Church in the United States published by the Quenzel Printing House in Martinsburg, W.Va. in 1892. The other two items are 1919 and 1922 annual reports of the Reformed Church of the U.S., representing St. Michael's Frieden's, Brown Memorial, and Island Ford Churches.
The collection also includes digitized material. Two accounting books belonging to C.L. Hedrick and George W. Hedrick, as well as a list of wedding gifts for Mr. and Mrs. John H. Sipe were scanned and returned to the donor. The "Miscellaneous" digitized items in this collection also have been photocopied and these copies are in the collection, including 19th Century letters and envelopes, a 1889 promissory note from George W. Hedrick to Abner Shacklett for $210.00, and a 1932 "Get Well Soon" card from Maud R. Lemley to Mrs. Annie Hedrick. Newspaper clippings from the Twin City Sentinel in Winston-Salem, NC regarding Pastor Dr. W. H. Causey are also included.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Bibliography
Wayland, John. A History of Rockingham County Virginia. Dayton, VA: Ruebush-Elkins Company, 1912.
Hammond's Edition of the 1885 Atlas of Rockingham County, Virginia. (from the 1885 surveys by J.M. Lathrop and B.N. Griffing; reproduced and compiled May, 1995 by GP Hammond Publishing.) Strasburg, VA: GP Hammond Publishing, 1995.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Financial statements -- Virginia; Elkton (Va.) -- History -- Sources; Rockingham County (Va.) -- History -- Sources
Genre and Form Terms:
Letters (correspondence)
- Correspondence, 1856–1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Account Book 1, 1857–1888 (Box SC0171-SET-001)
- Miscellaneous, 1857-1932 (Box 1, Folder 2, Box SC0171-SET-001)
- Court Summons, 1870–1882 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Business Records Receipts, 1874–1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Bank Promissory Notes, 1881–1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Account Book 2, 1882–1885 (Box SC0171-SET-001)
- Tax Receipts, 1884–1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Reformed Church, Rockingham Charge Reports, 1892-1922 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Wedding Gift Record of Mr. and Mrs. John H. Sipe, 1919 (Box SC0171-SET-001)